North Korea Subject Files, Inclusive: 1964-2004, Bulk: 1977-1998
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
North Korea Subject Files
Inclusive: 1964-2004, Bulk: 1977-1998
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
8
Keston Institute, 1969 -
2 A4 document boxes
The North Korea Subject Files contain a variety of materials pertaining to religion, North Korean leaders, and the country’s relations with South Korea and other countries.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the name changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist and totalitarian countries. The Keston Archive and Library houses numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals. Keston collected documents dating between 1964 and 2004 reflecting the political, as well as the religious climate of the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK) or North Korea.
Following World War II, the Korean peninsula was split between the northern DPRK under Soviet-sponsored communist control and the southern US-backed Republic of Korea. North Korea was established as a communist regime in 1948 under the leadership of Kim Il-Sung. In 1950, South Korea declared its independence which led to North Korea’s invasion and the beginning of the Korean War. After reaching an armistice in 1953, North Korea saw a period of significant industrial growth.
During the 1980s, North Korea was linked to acts of terrorism against South Korea, including the bombing of Korean Air Flight 858 and an assassination attempt on President Chun Doo-hwan in Rangoon, Burma (now Myanmar). With nuclear arms becoming an increasing concern for world leaders, North Korea signed the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty in 1985 which barred the country from producing nuclear weapons. However, the following year a research nuclear reactor became operational at the Yongbyon Nuclear Science Center.
The 1990s saw heightened tensions between North and South Korea. The United Nations accepted both nations for membership in 1991. In the 1980s, Kim Jong-il had been designated to succeed his father, and when Kim Il-sung died in 1994, Kim Jong-il became supreme leader of the DPRK. In 1996, North Korea experienced widespread famine and floods, and an estimated 3 million died. That same year, North Korea announced it would no longer abide by the armistice that ended the Korean War, and thousands of troops entered the demilitarized zone.
A landmark inter-Korean summit took place in 2000. At the meeting in Pyongyang, North Korean leader Kim Jong-il and South Korean President Kim Dae-jung paved the way for reopening border offices and facilitating family reunions. Although the summit brought hope of cordial relations, the following decade saw military and political battles between North Korea, South Korea and the rest of the world. In 2002, United States President George W. Bush labeled North Korea part of an “axis of evil” along with Iraq and Iran. In 2003, nearly 20 years after signing the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty, North Korea withdrew from the agreement. Within a year, Pyongyang declared the reprocessing of 8,000 spent nuclear fuel rods, providing enough weapons-grade plutonium to develop six nuclear bombs. In 2005, North Korea admitted to the production of nuclear weapons for “self-defense.” The following year, the country tested its first nuclear weapons at an underground facility. In response, the UN imposed economic and commercial sanctions.
In 2007 because of significant economic issues, North Korea agreed to shut down its main reactor at Yongbyon after receiving 50,000 tons of heavy fuel oil as part of an aid package. The North appealed for flood relief, and South Korea sent nearly $50 million in aid. In 2008, the United States removed North Korea from the terrorism blacklist in exchange for providing full access to the Yongbyon nuclear site. After launching a long-range rocket carrying what was described as a communications satellite, neighboring countries accused North Korea of testing long-range missile technology. These actions led to condemnation by the United Nations Security Council followed by North Korea walking out of six-party talks and officially restarting its nuclear facilities.
Kim Jong-il suffered a stroke in 2008, and after his death in 2011, his son Kim Jong-un became the supreme leader of North Korea.
Scope and Content
North Korea subject files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, news reports, and background briefs.
The materials cover the period from 1964-2004 with the bulk from 1977-1998. The majority pertain to Kim Il-sung, Kim Jong-il, international relations with South Korea and other countries, and religion.
Materials focusing on the events under the rules of Kim Il-sung and Kim Jong-il related to the established government, succession, and the general state of the country. Items depicting the relationship between North and South Korea discuss the reunification of the countries, the demilitarized zone, the 1988 Olympics in Seoul, and political relations. Other materials dealing with international relations include the United States, United Kingdom, Soviet Union, and China. Information regarding the religious state of North Korea contains resources on Catholics and Baptists. Other subjects encompass individual religious figures, oppressive practices related to religious activity, conversions, and the opening of churches.
Arrangement
The Keston center received the North Korea materials organized by categories. Within these categories, materials were arranged chronologically. This organization has mostly been preserved but has been divided further into specific thematic subjects.
The North Korea Subject Files are currently arranged in one series: I. General
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 8.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Kim, Chng-il, 1942-2011.; Kim, Il-sng, 1912-1994.
Subjects (Organizations)
Catholic Church -- Korea (North); Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.
Places
Korea (North) -- Economic conditions.; Korea (North) -- Foreign relations -- Korea (South); Korea (North) -- Foreign relations.; Korea (North) -- History -- 1948-1994.; Korea (North) -- History -- 1994-2011.; Korea (North) -- Politics and government -- 1948-1994.; Korea (North) -- Politics and government -- 1994-2011.; Korea (North) -- Religion.; Korea (South) -- Foreign relations -- Korea (North); Korean Demilitarized Zone (Korea)
Subjects
Baptists -- Korea (North); Church and State -- Korea (North); Civil rights and socialism -- Korea (North); Communism -- Korea (North); Famines -- Korea (North); Food relief -- Korea (North); Freedom of religion -- Korea (North); Korean reunification question (1945-); Persecution -- Korea (North)
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.)
- General, 1964-2004; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Scope and Content
  General North Korea subject files contain information on the history of the county, Kim Il-Sung, Kim Jong-il, the government, international relations, foreign aid, refugees, and religion.
  - General, 1976-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Individuals: Kim Dae Jung, 1984-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Individuals: Kim Il Sung, 1975-1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Individuals: Kim Jong Il, 1980-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Government, 1977-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Elections, 1977-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Military Affairs, 1977-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Espionage, 1983-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Constitution, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Basic Rights and Freedoms, 1987-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Citizens Alliance for North Korean Human Rights, 1999-2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices, 1982-2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Political Prisoners and Imprisonment, 1979-1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - International Relations, General, 1975-1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - International Relations: Burma, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - International Relations: China, 1984-1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - International Relations: Hungary, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - International Relations: Japan, 1988-1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - International Relations: South Korea, 1974-2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - International Relations: Soviet Union, 1984-2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - International Relations: United Kingdom, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - International Relations: United States, 1982-1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - International Relations: Vatican, 1987-2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Western Reactions, Interventions, Protests, and Criticisms, 1984-2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Visits, 1977-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Defections, 1982-2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Religion: General, 1964-2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Religious Individuals: Graham, Billy, 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Religious Individuals: Reverend Moon Ik-won, 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Religious Individuals: Reverend Sun Myung Moon, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ecumenical Movement, 1978-1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bibles, 1995-2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Opening of Churches, 1976-1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Conversions, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Visits by Religious Delegations, 1982-2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices Relating to Religious Activity, 1972-2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Baptists, 1989-2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Catholics, 1980-2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Religious Statistics, 1982-1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Communism, Socialism, and Juche, 1969-1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Propaganda, 1965-1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Agriculture, Economy, and Labor, 1983-1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Educational Institutions and Programs, 1973-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Tourism, 1987-1998 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sport, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Youth, Children, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 23)